Look at this, Koji! This doll's hair grows.
浩二 快过来看
Really?
真的假的？
Twenty on the scare meter.
惊吓程度20%
What a bore you are. At least act a little scared.
一点也不可爱 至少装出有点害怕的样子吗
You are a kid, after all.
你毕竟还是个孩子
Lady Mayonaka is way scarier.
午夜幽灵更加可怕
Who's Lady Mayonaka?
什么是午夜幽灵？
She's a woman with really long hair
一个头发很长的的女人
who stands at the shrine in the middle of the night.
半夜会站在神社前
This woman, she holds a doll.
这个女人会抱着一个人偶
If you look closely at the doll,
如果你仔细看这个人偶
its face is exactly like the woman's!
会发现人偶的脸和那个女人一模一样
-It's Lady Mayonaka!
-是午夜幽灵！
Really? That's Lady Mayonaka?
真的吗？这就是午夜幽灵啊
My friends at school saw her.
我同学看到她的
A long-haired woman?
头发很长的女人啊
The doll's hair grows.
人偶的头发变长了
The doll's hair grows?
人偶的头发会变长？
-Mr. Hirayama. -What?
-大叔 -怎么了？
-Your head.
-你的头 -什么？
Your head.
你的头
My hair… It's growing!
我的…我的头发变长了！
It's growing!
变长了
It's seaweed.
是海苔啦
-Seaweed? -Seaweed.
-海苔？ -海苔
Yes, it is seaweed.
确实是海苔
What do you want so early?
一大早有什么事？
-Time for a meeting. -What for?
-要开会了 -为什么要开会？
We're Nobuta's producers, right?
我们要改造野猪 对吗？
Yes, I did say that, but it doesn't mean you can come to my house.
我确实说过 但不代表你可以来我家
How come? We're best friends.
为什么？我们是好朋友啊
I told you. We're not best friends.
我说过我们不是好朋友
Hey, wait up, man!
等一下
Come on! Wait up!
等一下啦
Hey. Excuse me, please.
等等 不好意思
Hanging out with a guy like you doesn't do me any good at all.
跟你这种人混在一起 对我一点好处都没有
There's only one thing I'm after.
我只追求一件事
To play the popular guy, Shuji, while enjoying life at school.
就是扮演人见人爱的修二 同时享受着校园生活
Morning four meters!
早安 四米
-There it is! A new record!
-来了 刷新纪录！
-Hey, Shuji. -Yes?
-修二 -什么？
You know Lady Mayonaka?
你知道午夜幽灵吗？
You bet. She's that woman with a doll at the shrine.
当然 就是在神社 抱着人偶的那个女人
-Oh, man! You know? -Of course.
-原来你知道啊 -当然
Did you know this? Who is Lady Mayonaka for real?
你们知道午夜幽灵到底是谁吗？
-Who is it? -I heard it's Nobuko Kotani.
-是谁？ -听说是小谷信子
-For real? -Seriously?
-真的吗？
Are you sure?
你确定吗？
Lady Mayonaka!
午夜幽灵
CURSED
（诅咒）
Turn this bullied girl into the most popular girl in school?
把这个被霸凌的女生 变成全校最受欢迎的女生？
I can't believe I promised to do that.
真不敢相信我答应要做这件事
DIE
（去死）
Why the heck did I say that?
我到底为什么要答应？
This…
我真是…
Sucks.
糟透了
PARENT-TEACHER CONFERENCE NOTICE
（家长座谈会通知）
Why are you wearing that?
你为什么穿成那样？
Oh, yes.
这个啊
Pretty cool, right?
帅吗？
-You're going to work in that? -I sure am.
-你要穿成那样去上班？ -没错
-No way! That's so totally tacky! -Morning.
-不要啊 太老土了 -早安
Quit whining! What's wrong with it?
你好吵 有什么问题吗？
-What crazy clothes! -What?
-好怪的衣服 -什么？
Oh, just cut it out.
别吵
Kids don't know what's good.
小孩子不懂什么叫帅气
Yes, we do. That's just plain weird. Right?
我们懂啊 这样穿太奇怪了 对吗？
-Yes. It's awful. -Just awful.
-对啊 糟透了 -糟透了
I'll have you guys know, I'm going to the parent-teacher conference in this.
你们要知道 我要穿这样去家长座谈会
No way! It's too early for that!
真的啊？一大清早的
Please don't! I'll die!
拜托不要 我会丢脸死的
Hey.
喂
-Shuji. -What?
-哥 -怎么了？
Someone's downstairs asking for you.
楼下有人找你
It's way too early for this.
一大清早的
That's for sure.
是真的
Shuji!
修二
Yip yip!
嗯嗯
Before rumors of Lady Mayonaka spread, we need to put an end to it.
在午夜幽灵的谣言传开前 必须先做个了结
Do you have a plan?
你有计划吗？
Well, I do have something.
我是有计划啦
Excellent. I always knew you had it in you.
太好啦 我一直都知道你有这个本事
Oh, yeah. But first, this.
对啦 但你们先看看这个
I made some rules to follow to make you popular.
我为了让你受欢迎制定了一些规则
Nice.
很好
"One! Absolutely never mention that we're producing you!"
“一 绝对不能提 我们要改造你的事”
It's best if you read it out loud yourself. Okay?
还是你自己念出来较好 对吗？
Right.
是的
"One. Absolutely never mention that we're producing you.
“一 绝对不能提我们要改造你的事
Two. You can never refuse to do what the producers tell you to do.
二 我们对你进行的改造 一律不得拒绝
Three. Never act without permission.
三 不能擅自行动
Four. Our contract ends when you become popular.
四 你变得受欢迎之后 合约就终止
At the very least, we need you to follow those rules.
你最起码必须遵守这些规则
I know this is sudden, but let's chop off that hair.
虽然很突然 你还是把头发剪掉哦
What?
什么？
What are you so surprised about?
你有什么好惊讶的？
But a woman's hair is her pride. Right?
但是头发是女人的自尊啊 对吗？
You mean you like your hair that way?
你喜欢留这种发型吗？
Actually, I hate it.
其实我很讨厌这个发型
Then let's do it.
那就剪掉呀
Split ends.
发尾分叉了
Why not?
为什么？
I just can't do it on my own.
我不能自己剪头发
-Look. Split ends. -What?
-发尾分叉了 -什么？
This hair is cursed!
我的头发被诅咒了
She totally said it was cursed.
她说头发被诅咒了
I was totally touching her cursed split ends!
我还摸了她被诅咒的分叉发尾
Whoa! That's awesome!
太棒啦！
Shuji!
修二
Your lady's here.
你女朋友来了
-I made meatballs today. -What?
-我今天做了肉丸哦 -什么？
By the way, with girls…
对啦
Cutting your hair is a pretty serious thing, right?
剪头发是一件很重要的事吗？
You bet it's serious.
当然是很重要啊
Is that right?
是吗？
But if you wanted me to cut it, Shuji, then I would.
不过修二让我剪的话 我就会剪
-Want me to cut it? -No.
-要我剪短吗？ -不用
-Shuji.
-你要我剪短吗？ -修二
Shuji.
修二
The mystery's been solved.
谜团解开了
I know what the curse is!
我知道诅咒是什么了
"Curse"?
诅咒？
What? Hey!
什么？喂
-I'll be back in a second. -That's good!
-我马上回来 -真好吃
-I'll be right back. -What is that? It's great!
-那是什么？真好吃
-Red miso? White miso? -Forget that!
-红味噌？白味噌？ -好啦
-Blue miso? No such thing! -Don't cut your hair!
-蓝味噌？没有那种东西 -不要剪头发哦
-See you! -Don't cut it! If you cut it, I'll cry!
-别剪 你剪了我会哭哦 -再见
I'll cry until I ran out of tears!
我会嚎啕大哭哦
Hello!
嗨
I knew it. You're Lady Mayonaka.
你果然就是午夜幽灵
Is this why you won't cut your hair?
这就是你不剪头发的原因吗？
It has to be just like hers.
我的发型必须跟人偶一样
It totally looks like you.
它看起来真的和你很像
She's my one and only friend.
它是我唯一的朋友
What? This is your friend?
什么？这是你的朋友？
Your friend is a doll? Hilarious.
你的朋友是人偶？真好笑
She's seen all the times I've been bullied.
我每次被霸凌 它都看在眼里
She's always encouraged me.
它总是鼓励我
But that's still no reason to always keep it around.
但还是没有理由把它带在身边啊
I've tried to get rid of it and took it to a shrine,
我试过要把它处理掉 还把它带去神社
That's no curse. It's a spell you put on yourself.
那不是诅咒 是你对自己施的咒
I can't change and leave her behind.
我不能改变 丢下它不管
I see.
这样啊
Okay. I've got an idea.
好 我知道啦
Is this about the length you want?
这个长度可以吗？
How about it? Is this good?
怎么样？这样可以吗？
Can you make it a little more shaggy?
可以弄得更蓬松一点吗？
-Shaggy? Okay. -One shaggy, coming up!
-蓬松吗？好的 -蓬松一下
Akiko Yada, please.
矢田亚希子 麻烦你啦
-Like Akiko Yada? -Yes, Akiko Yada.
-要像矢田亚希子那样？ -对 矢田亚希子
She doesn't know what that means.
她不懂那是什么意思啦
It's done! Smooch!
完成了 亲一个
How pretty.
好可爱
You bet.
对吗
You can cut your hair now, right?
你现在可以剪头发了吗？
-What? -Wait!
-什么？ -等一下
Hey!
喂
I thought you said it had to be like the doll's.
你不是说一定要跟人偶一样吗？
-But I still don't want to get it cut. -Why?
-但我还是不想剪头发 -为什么？
I don't think I can do something different than what I like.
我没办法做我不喜欢的事
Then what do you like?
那你喜欢什么？
If this rumor keeps spreading, you'll be treated like a monster forever.
如果这种谣言继续流传下去 你会一辈子被当作妖怪的
Now just calm down, Shuji.
修二 你先冷静一下
What?
-怎么啦？ -那么…
Would you wear that?
你们会穿那个吗？
To me, cutting my hair is the same as you doing that.
对我来说 剪头发就跟叫你们穿那种衣服一样
Fine. Whatever.
算了 我知道啦
Let's end this.
让我们结束这一切
End what?
结束什么？
This whole thing about producing her.
改造她的事
What?
什么？
There's no point if she won't follow the rules.
她不遵守规则就没意义啦
Hold on there.
等一下
Hey, both of you!
喂 你们两个
Wait!
等一下啦
He called me "Jaiko"!
他叫我技安妹
"Jaiko"? For a nickname?
技安妹？是绰号吗？
That would make anyone mad.
谁听到都会生气
It ticked me off.
气死我了
How could someone say that?
怎么会有人说这种话？
That's awful.
好过分
Why am I hiding?
我为什么要躲起来？
Yes, that's hilarious.
对啊 真好笑
And you know what? Shuji said he'd cry if I cut my hair.
你们知道吗？ 修二说如果我剪头发他会哭
Then cut it and make him cry.
那就剪啊 把他弄哭
Good idea! I'll make him cry!
好主意 那我来把他弄哭
This sucks.
真差劲
What will you buy?
你要买什么？
Roasted green tea? Whole green tea?
焙茶？煎茶？
Or maybe refined green tea?
还是玉露呀？
The one I want to cut her hair won't
我想让剪头发的那位不剪
and the one who doesn't need to will.
没必要剪的人却要剪
What the heck's going on?
这是怎么回事？
Maybe I will cry!
我真的要哭了
I'm home.
我回来啦
-You're home early today? -Yes.
-今天这么早回来啊？ -对啊
What's the matter?
怎么啦？
That. Everybody totally hated it.
大家都很讨厌那套衣服
Well, of course, they did.
那是当然啦
Shuji.
修二
Wear what you want while you can.
趁现在尽量穿自己爱穿的衣服
When you grow up, things like people's opinions, common sense,
长大之后 就要顾虑别人的意见和世俗的观点
a good image, your boss's mood, your impression on clients…
自己的形象 老板的心情 还有你给客户的印象
All those things weigh you down so you can't wear what you like.
那些东西让你变得沉重 不能再穿喜欢的衣服
Dad.
爸
Wear that to the parent-teacher conference.
穿那套衣服去参加家长座谈会
Okay.
好
What?
什么？
I can?
可以吗？
Well, I don't really like it though.
虽然你我不怎么喜欢
-Then forget it. -It's okay.
-那就算啦 -没关系
It is?
可以吗？
Wear it to the parent-teacher conference.
穿去参加家长座谈会哦
Maybe I shouldn't go saying stuff about other people's taste.
或许我不该去批评别人的品味
Get your act together, people!
打起精神来 各位
Show some spirit, even if it's fake!
拿出精神 至少也要装装样子啊
Oh, dear!
天啊
-Bye!
-再见
Kusano! Show some spirit!
草野 打起精神来
-Can I borrow your deodorant? -Sure!
-我能借用你的体香剂吗？ -当然可以
Bando. You sure you've taken enough PE to graduate?
坂东 你上体育课的次数 足够让你毕业吗？
-Everyone says that. Is it bad? -Yes, it's really bad.
-大家都这么说 很不妙吗？ -对 真的很不妙
I guess I can't use that excuse anymore.
我再也不能用这个借口啦
Yes, you can't. No way.
对 不能用啦 不行
-You sure can't. You got deodorant? -Yes, I do.
-当然不行 你有体香剂吗？ -有啊 我有
-Can I use it? -Sure.
-我可以用吗？ -好啊
-You've skipped a lot too. -No, I've done PE plenty.
-你也翘了很多堂课 -没有 我上了很多体育课
You're just leaving me behind and throwing away…
你就这样抛下我
-Kiritani. -Here.
-桐谷 -在
-Kusano.
-草野
Kotani.
小谷
-Kondo. -Here.
-近藤 -在
Wait.
等等
Where's Kotani?
小谷在哪？
She was here this morning. Anyone know where she is?
她今天早上来了啊 有人知道她在哪里吗？
Well, all right then. Sato.
好 接下来是佐藤
-Here. -Takada.
-在 -高田
No way. That sucks.
不会啊 太差劲啦
Who would do that?
谁会做这种事？
I bet it was those guys.
我猜一定是她们
In fact, they're the only ones who would.
只有她们会做那种事
Hey, you bitches!
喂 你们这些贱人
Don't blame every damn thing on us!
别什么事都怪到我们头上
We never did that shit!
我们才没做那种事
-What's going on? -Misaki and Nami are screwed!
-怎么回事？ -美咲和奈美完蛋啦
-Attack, Shuji! -What? Why me?
-修二 上啊！ -什么？为什么是我？
What? What's going on?
什么？怎么回事？
-They're ticking us off! -What for?
-她们把我们惹毛啦 -为什么？
They painted "ugly pig" on Kotani's uniform!
她们在小谷的制服上写“丑猪”
You did that?
是你们做的？
The fuck we did! We wouldn't do that!
别乱说 我们才不会那么做
-That's right! The hell we did! -Anyone could have done it!
-对啊 最好是啦 -可能是任何人写的
All right. All right.
我知道啦
You're right. You've got a bad attitude and bad looks, but you'd never lie.
也对 虽然你态度和外观都像个坏人 但绝对不会说谎
I told you. We didn't do it!
我不是说过了吗？不是我们做的
-That's right! -They say they didn't.
-没错 -她们说不是她们
-Did you? -I told you, no!
-是吗？ -我说啦 不是我们
We didn't do it!
不是我们
"We didn't do it!"
“不是我们”
What're we going to do about being her producers?
我们要怎么改造她呀？
I told you. Buzz off!
我不是说过了吗？别跟过来
Dang it! What about being her producers?
讨厌 那改造她的事该怎么办？
Hey, come on.
喂 等一下啊
Whoa! No U-turns!
禁止掉头
I told you. Watch out!
我不是说了吗？危险
Come on, Shuji. Where we going?
修二 我们要去哪里？
Tell me!
告诉我啊
Watch out.
危险
Can I ask a favor?
能请你帮个忙吗？
Can I borrow some money?
可以借我一点钱吗？
Sure.
好啊
Thank you. I'll pay you back.
谢谢 我会还你的
Yip yip.
嗯嗯
Nobuta!
野猪
Say…
我说啊
Let's cut your hair.
我们去剪头发
Cut your hair and show everyone you're not an ugly pig.
把头发剪掉 让大家看看你不是丑猪
You know, any way you look at it, yours is way prettier.
不管怎么看 还是你那件比较可爱
They're the same!
都一样啦
-I mean, this thing is pink! -Yes, but mine's green.
-但我这件是粉红色的 -我是绿色的啊
Zip this up. Hurry. Zip it up.
把衣服穿好 快点穿好
What's wrong?
怎么啦？
That's how she looks when she smiles.
她笑起来就是这种表情
She's smiling!
她笑了
Poke.
我靠
We got a smile!
看到笑容啦
I…
我…
I'll cut my hair.
我会去剪头发
Please.
拜托你们啦
Sure thing.
没问题
UGLY PIG
（丑猪）
Right when we were going to change her image,
偏偏挑在我们要改变她形象的时候
this sure won't help.
这样肯定没帮助
You know, I was thinking, and this could be our chance.
我在想这可能是我们的机会
"This"? You mean this?
“这个”？这个吗？
Let's see…
我来看看…
"Students must wear their uniform.
“学生必须穿着制服
However, if the uniform is unable to be worn for some reason,
但如果因为某些原因不能穿制服
immediately submit an application for wearing ordinary clothes.
应立刻提交穿便服的申请
Only upon approval may ordinary clothes be worn."
获准后就能穿便服”
Clearly, you can't wear this.
你已经不能穿这制服啦
Isn't that right?
对吗？
In other words, as long as they give approval,
也就是说 只要学校同意
you can wear ordinary clothes to school.
你就可以穿便服去学校
Right. So you should wear totally pretty clothes to school.
对 所以去学校一定要穿漂亮的衣服
Then the school would go crazy.
然后就能在学校造成轰动
This really is awful.
这真的太过分啦
And you don't have any idea who did this?
你真的不知道是谁做的？
And there's no way we can figure out who did it.
但我们也没办法查出是谁做的
Anyway, I'll report to the principal that this happened.
总之这件事我会向校长报告
Go on.
你可以离开了
I need approval.
我需要同意书
Yes. Oh, yes.
对 好
Oh, darn. The principal went home.
糟糕 校长回家了
Is tomorrow all right?
明天再签可以吗？
-Mr. Yokoyama. -Yes?
-横山老师 -是？
You want her to wear that to school again tomorrow?
你要她明天也穿那样来学校吗？
But we need the principal's seal.
但我们需要校长的印章
If someone painted "coward" on your suit, could you teach like that?
如果有人在你的西装上写了胆小鬼 你也会穿着教书吗？
"Coward"?
“胆小鬼”？
I'll take responsibility.
这件事我会负责
Oh, thank you.
拜托你啦
Wear the prettiest clothes you can tomorrow.
明天穿上最漂亮的衣服来学校
And give the finger to whoever did that.
然后对做出这种事的人比个中指
Yes!
好耶
This is what I recommend.
我推荐这件上衣
It would go nice with jeans too.
搭牛仔裤应该也不错
-Over there… -What?
-那边… -什么？
There's an expensive book there. Be careful with it.
-有一本很贵的书 小心点 -好的
-There's an expensive book. -An expensive book?
-他说有一本很贵的书 -很贵的书？
I wonder which one it is.
不知道是哪一本？
PRICE: 100,000,000 YEN (TAX NOT INCLUDED)
（价格 一亿日元 未税）
A hundred million yen?
一亿日元？
A hundred million?
一亿？
It's by Delphine Sakurada.
作者是戴菲尼樱田
-You know them? -No.
-你不认识他？ -不认识
That's my pen name.
那是我的笔名
Delphine?
戴菲尼？
-Holy cow! We'll choose from these? -Yes.
-天啊 要从这里面选吗？ -对
First, we need to decide how you want people to see you.
首先 我们要决定 你希望大家怎么看你
How about like this, the honor-student type?
这样如何？优等生风格
Teachers and parents would really like you.
老师和家长应该都会很喜欢你
Right? Okay.
对吗？好
Or if you want to look cute, angel style.
还是想打扮的可爱点 走天使风？
If you want to express individuality, this little-devil style.
如果想要有点个性 就选这种小恶魔风格
I like this!
我喜欢这个
This looks like a total slut. No way. Nothing slutty.
这个看起来像个荡妇 不行 不能穿太暴露
Rejected.
驳回
I didn't realize
我都不知道
there were so many styles.
有这么多种风格
Really? It's the same with guys.
真的吗？男生也一样啊
I mean, there are crew cuts, but…
就拿平头来说
there's the classy crew cut done at a hair salon, right?
有在发廊剪的时尚感平头 对吗？
Then there's the country bumpkin crew cut for guys who don't want to bother.
也有平价理发店剪的乡巴佬平头
And there's the refreshing crew cut for guys into sports.
还有运动风的清爽平头
And the frightening crew cut for guys who stare you down.
还有凶狠的帮派风平头
I've never thought about it.
我没想过啊
Listen.
听着
That's the only thing that everyone at school thinks about.
学校里每个人都只在乎这件事
"I want to be liked."
“我想要被人喜欢”
"I don't want to be made fun of."
“我不想被取笑”
"I want everyone to pay attention to me."
“我要大家注意我”
Everyone's focusing totally on that stuff.
大家满脑子都在想这种事
So you also need to think about that kind of stuff,
所以你也得思考这些事
even just a little bit. Okay?
要花点心思 好吗？
Of course you want guys to like you,
你当然会希望男生喜欢你
but if girls don't like you too, you'll never make points.
但如果女生不喜欢你的话 也就没有意义啦
You bet. I thought up a plan too. Have a look.
当然啦 我想了一个计划 你们看
Here. See?
看到了吗？
Nice. Awesome!
很好 太棒啦
Want to do this?
你想这么做吗？
I don't think anyone's actually got self-confidence.
我认为没有人是真正有自信的
We're all timid.
大家都很害羞
We can barely handle dealing with ourselves.
我们连自己都照顾不好
We don't have time to think about others.
没时间管别人
So there's no need to be afraid.
所以你不用害怕
First, don't worry about getting people to like you.
首先 别去想着要别人喜欢你
Get everyone to realize that you just exist.
只要让大家知道你的存在就好
No way!
真的假的？
Okay. Put your chest out!
好 挺胸
More! Stand up straight.
抬头挺胸
When you greet people, speak up!
打招呼的时候要大点声
Remember that.
记好啦
Okay. Go on now.
好 去呀
Stand up straighter.
打起精神来
Bye.
再见
Listen.
听着
You exist. That's all you need to think about.
你只需要记住自己是存在的
Morning.
早安
-Good morning. -Morning.
-早安
Good morning.
早安
"Good morning"?
“早安”？
I exist!
我是存在的
Good…
早…
How cute!
-好可爱 -我喜欢
-She's so pretty! -I totally like it!
-她好漂亮 -我超喜欢的
Why is she in ordinary clothes?
她怎么穿便服？
-Hey, baby! -Nice!
-喂 宝贝 -真漂亮
Who are you?
你是谁？
That's Kotani!
是小谷
Hey, look at this.
你看这个
That's this jacket in another color.
是这件外套的另一个颜色
-No way! -25,200 yen?
-真假？ -两万五千两百日元？
-Let's ask!
-不可能呀 -我们去问问看
Wait!
等等
Was that jacket 25,200 yen?
你那件外套是两万五千两百日元吗？
I knew it! That's it!
我就知道是同款
It's way better than the photo!
比照片好看多啦
Totally!
没错
Hello!
早安
She cut her hair.
她剪头发啦
If she were sushi, she'd be otoro from the Indian Ocean!
如果她是寿司 就是印度洋的金枪鱼大腹肉
-Otoro! -Good morning!
-金枪鱼大腹肉 -早安
The king of toro!
金枪鱼大腹肉之王
I can't hear you!
声音太小啦
-This is incredible! -Holy cow!
-不得了 -天啊
Hello!
大家好
I never thought Kotani could undergo such a transformation!
没想到小谷竟然会有那样的转变
It's a miracle!
真是奇迹
Cute! Totally cute!
真可爱 超可爱
Nobuko, you're pretty! Nobuko!
信子 你好漂亮 信子
Holy cow!
天啊
Glug…
咕噜
That's awesome.
真好喝
Awesome!
好喝
-You know those clothes that Kotani wore? -Yes?
-你知道小谷穿的衣服吗？ -怎么啦？
They were a lot like those clothes that I suggested.
跟我推荐的衣服很像
-Really? Is that right? -Yes.
-真的吗？是吗？ -对啊
I totally didn't notice. You've got a good eye.
我完全没注意到 你眼力真好
What's more, those fundamentals I talked about,
而且我说过的基本要素
she had them down to a tee without missing a thing.
她完全掌握 没有漏掉任何一点
Kotani's got such great fashion sense, why was she the way she was?
既然小谷这么有时尚品味 为什么她之前会那样？
Right?
是啊
-Let's get monjayaki! -Yes! Let's!
-我们去吃文字烧 -好耶 走呀
Let's go!
走呀
Shit…
该死
-Your treat. -You bet!
-你请客 -当然
-You want rice cakes on it? -Yes!
-要加麻薯吗？ -要
DANI
（小蝨）
-Good morning. -Morning.
-早安
Morning.
早安
Can I wear ordinary clothes from tomorrow?
明天开始我可以穿便服吗？
I guess you'll have to.
我想也只能这样啦
Morn…
早…
Principal Iehara, can I get your seal on these?
家原校长 这些请你盖印章
Okay.
好
-What is it? -Can you wait a second?
-怎么啦？ -能等一下吗？
What's this?
这是什么？
A picture of a raccoon dog?
这画的是狸猫吗？
That's not a raccoon dog. That's Hello Kitty.
这不是狸猫 这是凯蒂猫
-You idiot. -What?
-你这个笨蛋 -什么？
What's going on?
怎么回事？
How can you know that if you didn't draw it?
又不是你画的 你怎么知道？
I just thought that's what it looked like.
我只是觉得看起来很像啊
See that? She's wearing a ribbon.
看到了吗？它戴着蝴蝶结
We cannot authorize it if you drew it yourselves!
如果衣服是自己画的 我们不会签同意书
-You've got to be kidding!
-怎么会？
Chie!
知惠
-We didn't get approval!
-我们没拿到同意书
No way! I just painted on mine!
怎么会啊？我才刚画好
What will I tell my mom?
我要怎么跟我妈说？
Let's get our parents help. Get photos with our phones.
现在只能跟父母求救了 去拿手机
She drew it herself. "Proof"?
那是她自己画的 证据？
I don't have any.
我没有
Sorry.
抱歉
Sorry. Bye.
抱歉 再见
A parent, right? What'd they say?
是家长吗？他们怎么说？
"It's unfair just one kid gets to wear ordinary clothes."
“只有一个孩子能穿便服 太不公平啦”
Everyone in class is getting upset!
班上的同学开始闹啦
You let one person wear ordinary clothes, but nobody else? That's just not right.
你们只让一个人穿便服 其他人都不行 这样不对呀？
-Right? -That's right!
-对吗？ -没错
Let us wear ordinary clothes too!
也让我们穿便服
I can't wear this uniform!
-我不能穿这件制服
Without even trying to understand how the bullied person feels,
你们没有试着去了解被霸凌者的心情
you're trying to take advantage of what she got.
只想利用她来达到目的
I won't stand for that kind of attitude.
我不能接受这种态度
How do you know that Kotani didn't paint it herself?
你怎么知道小谷的制服 不是自己画的？
That's right.
-就是说啊
-You don't have proof. -Yes! That's right!
-你没有证据 -没错 说得对
Just looking at it. You can tell!
光看就能看得出来
Isn't that just your personal view?
那只是你个人的看法呀？
That's not scientific.
一点都不科学
That's right.
没错
At any rate, we cannot give approval if you ruined your uniform yourself.
总之我们不会同意 自己画制服的人穿便服来学校
From now on,
从现在开始
you're deeply mistaken if you think you can get away with tricks like that!
要是你们以为能耍这种小伎俩 来达到目的 那就大错特错
I'm not going to back down.
我不会通融的
Quiet down now!
安静 全都给我安静
Kotani. What's wrong?
小谷 怎么啦？
Well…
那个…
I…
我…
I'll wear my uniform from tomorrow.
我明天开始会穿制服
Is that really what you want?
你真的想那么做吗？
Is everyone else fine with that?
其他人都没意见？
Is this the fairness that you're all clamoring for?
这就是你们吵着要的公平吗？
Well, since it is what Kotani wants,
好 既然小谷都这么说啦
we won't be approving ordinary clothes for anyone.
我们不会允许任何人穿便服来学校
Whoever painted on her uniform must be very pleased right now.
画她制服的人现在一定很开心
Buta! What'll you do now?
野猪 你现在打算怎么办？
It's okay.
没关系
What's okay?
什么没关系？
I'll dress cool like I did with ordinary clothes.
我会跟穿便服时一样酷
You know that's impossible.
你知道那是不可能的
That's right. It says "ugly pig" all across the back.
对啊 你的制服后面写着“丑猪”
What's that?
那是什么？
This boy is wearing the PE uniform I wore in elementary school.
这个男孩穿着我小学时的体育服
You're right.
真的呀
TICK
（小蝨）
Her name's been changed to "tick."
他的名字被改成“小蝨”啦
The bullying then was the worst.
那时受到的霸凌是最严重的
I wanted…
当时的我…
to die.
只想死
-Tick!
-小蝨
-Give it here! -Don't!
-拿来 -不要
Tick! Tick!
-小蝨
Give it back!
还给我
Stop it!
住手
The PE uniform I threw out somehow ended up
被我丢掉的体育服
worn by a boy in Africa.
最后传给了一个非洲小男孩
What's more, he's smiling while wearing it.
但是他穿的很开心
I bet
我想…
he'd be happy no matter what he wears.
他不管穿什么都很开心
He can live life happily.
他可以快乐地生活
Someone down there painted on her uniform.
乱画她制服的人就在那群人之中
"The culprit is among you!" Like that?
“犯人就在你们之中” 像这样吗？
I don't think I can stand for it to end like this.
我无法忍受这件事就这样过去
You got another idea?
你有别的主意吗？
Hit me with it! Come on!
说来听听 快
-Morning. -Good morning.
-早安
Okay.
好
Those guys are such idiots!
那些家伙真蠢
They really and truly are idiots!
真的是蠢到家啦
SNOB
（势利眼）
MORON
（笨蛋）
One, two, three, four.
一 二 三 四
Good morning.
早安
Eight days a week, hello!
一周八天 大家好
-What do you think? -What's that?
-你们觉得如何？ -那是什么？
-I'm going to start a fad. -That'll never be a fad!
-我要掀起一股风潮啦 -那种东西不会流行的
Morning!
早安
-I'll turn it into a huge fad! -Don't run in the hall!
-我会让它变得流行 -不要在走廊奔跑
Look! One idiot already copied me!
快看 已经有一个笨蛋学我啦
It's a fad. No doubt about it!
这肯定会引起一股潮流
Good morning.
早安
Morning.
-早
I'm not sure why, but after that,
不知道为什么 在那之后
it became a huge fad at our school.
这种行为在我们学校掀起了一股风潮
-Whoa! That's really nice!
-天啊 真帅啊！
-We're in sync. This must be destiny!
-心有灵犀 这一定是命运
-Uniforms are the best!
-制服最棒啦
Look! It's like Hermès.
快看 这跟爱马仕一样
I heard that Yamagata Prefecture grows the most.
我听说山形县增加最多
Seriously.
真的
LOVESICK
（相思病）
MANABU SATO
（佐藤学）
SURVIVAL OF THE FITTEST
（弱肉强食）
Things have gone crazy, right?
情况已经失控了 对吗？
What'll we do about this?
这下该怎么办？
Leave them be. They'll get sick of it soon.
别管他们 他们很快就腻了
Like Catherine said, the fad died out fast.
就像凯瑟琳说的 这股风潮很快就会褪去
-Here! Look at this. -Mr. Hirayama.
-你看这个 -大叔
That's not a fad anymore.
那已经不流行啦
What? You're kidding!
什么？真的假的？
No, I'm not kidding.
真的 我没在开玩笑
But two or three people still wear this stuff, right?
但还有两三个人会穿是吗？
Not a single person does.
一个人都没有
Back to work then.
我回去工作了
My dad showed up to the parent-teacher conference dressed like the mafia.
我爸打扮成黑手党来参加家长座谈会
Mr. Yokoyama, good…
横山老师 你…
Have a seat.
请坐
Nobuta is still as sulky as ever.
野猪仍像以前那样闷闷不乐
She's practicing how to smile now.
她正在练习怎么笑
Hey, quit making that disgusting face, Kotani.
别露出那么恶心的表情 小谷
And it's your fault that everyone blamed us for all that.
大家会怀疑我们都是你害的
Hey, Kotani. Apologize!
小谷 道歉啊
Apologize, you ugly pig!
快道歉 你这个丑猪
Ugly pig!
-丑猪
We're just saying what's true!
我们说的都是实话
You ugly pig. Say something!
丑猪 说话啊
SUMIDAGAWA HIGH SCHOOL FESTIVAL
（隅田川高中文化祭）
The festival?
文化祭？
I secretly sneered at people who want to make memories at the school festival.
我暗自嘲笑过 想在文化祭留下美好回忆的人
NINE DAYS UNTIL SUMIDAGAWA HIGH FESTIVAL
（隅田川高中文化祭倒数九天）
But this year's festival was special.
但今年的文化祭很特别
It was a festival
今年的文化祭
where everything was special…
一切都很特别
and hair-curling.
而且令人毛骨悚然
Oh, nice. A haunted house.
好棒啊 是鬼屋啊
If Nobuta's a success at the festival, everyone will see her differently.
如果野猪在文化祭上大放异彩 大家都会对她另眼相看
Make it couples only!
规定只限情侣参加
Kotani's the type that holds a grudge.
小谷是那种会记仇的人
What are you going to do, producer Shuji Kiritani?
改造者桐谷修二 你打算怎么做？
Subtitle translation by: Brian Athey
字幕翻译：张欣怡